New York Friends of Midwives; Records apap403
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
New York Friends of Midwives Records
1978-2010
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
apap403
1.19 cubic ft.
This collection documents the day-to-day activities of former advocacy organization, New York Friends of Midwives. New York Friends of Midwives advocated for the birthing rights of mothers and practicing midwives.
Content Description
This collection consists of newsletters, subject files, event files, research and history files.
Access
Access to this collection is unrestricted.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
All items in this collection were donated by Carolyn Keefe in March 2023.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized chronologically. There are no series.
Historical Note
Founded in 1993, New York Friends of Midwives was formerly the largest consumer advocacy organization for midwifery in the state. Through advocacy work, educational and public outreach, and political activities, the organization provided information about midwifery care and birthing alternatives; supported the independent role of midwives; worked with and challenged the State Board of Midwifery about licensing protocols and education for direct entry midwives; and advocated for midwives that were arrested as a result of the restrictions placed on direct-entry midwives under the Midwifery Practice Act of 1992.
New York Friends of Midwives; Midwives--New York (State); Medicine and Health Care; Women; Reproductive rights -- New York (State) -- History; Saratoga (N.Y.); Newsletters; Correspondence
- Historic Information, 1978-1997; Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Historic Information, Media, 1978-1997; Undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
- NAPSAC News, 1990; 1997; 2000-2001 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Legislative History of the Professional Midwifery Practice Act (1992), 1991-1997 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- New York Friends of Midwives "Birth & Women's Power," Ina May Gaskin, 1993 (Oversize 1)
- Advocacy for Direct Entry Midwives, 1993; Undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
- New York Board of Midwifery Meetings, 1993; 1999-2006; Undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Events, 1993-1994; 2000-2001; 2007 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Childbearing Policy within a National Health Program, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Unnecessary Cesarean Sections, 1994 (Oversize 1)
- New York Friends of Midwives Materials, Media Advisories, 1994; 1998; Undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
- About Midwife Arrests, 1994-1997; Undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
- New York Board of Midwifery Correspondence, 1994-1999; 2002-2005 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- New York Friends of Midwives "Midwifery Connection" Newsletter, 1995-1999 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- New York Friends of Midwives Media, 1995-1999; 2002-2004 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Midwifery in New York State: Comprehensive Report, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- About New York Friends of Midwives, 1996; 1999; Undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
- About Midwifery Certification, 1996; 1999; 2005 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- "Home Birth" Chapter Reprinted from The Five Standard for Safe Childbearing, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- "Midwifery" Chapter Reprinted from The Five Standard for Safe Childbearing, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Breaking the Barriers to Midwifery Access, 1997; 2000-2004; Undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
- New York Friends of Midwives Notes, 1997-1999; 2003-2005; Undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
- New York Friends of Midwives Correspondence, 1999; 2003-2006 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Legislative History of the Professional Midwifery Practice Act (1992), 1999-2002; Undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
- New York Friends of Midwives Materials, 2001-2004; Undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
- (brain)Storming the Barriers to Midwifery Access, 2002; Undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Midwifery Modernization Act Advocacy (2010), 2002; 2005; 2009-2010; Undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Midwifery Survey, 2002; 2006; Undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Midwifery Crisis in New York State, 2003; Undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
- New York State Association of Licensed Midwives Meetings, 2008-2009; Undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
- New York Friends of Midwives Stamp, Undated (Oversize 1)